hey guys coach Brett contas here um I
wanted to take some time to explain uh
some some considerations with queuing
and specifically the knees out queue
that all of us coaches um you know
provide for our for our clients and
athletes when they're
squatting so first thing that I want to
say about
queing
um I see a lot of coaches and trainers
make this mistake when they're
training their their athletes or clients
and they will especially when working
with a a beginner a novice and they'll
be telling them a cue during the
exercise but they didn't demonstrate it
beforehand and so the athlete is
confused and all you have to do it takes
two seconds and and trust me I've made
the mistake a million times as a trainer
and it always reminds me God you were
just being lazy but always take the time
to demonstrate it beforehand so if I um
am going over form you know you've got
to learn what this particular athlete
struggles with what this particular
client tends to how they tend to break
down and you need to keep a mental note
of that or at least make notes of it so
the next time you train them you can
glance over and say okay this is how
they tend to break down this is what I
need to remind them some people don't
need to be told to push through their
heels some people do some people don't
need to be told chest up some people
need to be told something else so you
should always learn how your athlete and
your client tend to you know break down
or exhibit energy leaks however you want
to call it and so you demonstrate it
beforehand and you explain to them
exactly what you mean so if you don't do
that for a squat and let's say you just
put a bar on your back okay and you tell
them all right remember knees out knees
out or say they do a rep say they do a
bad rep and then you go knees out KN
knees out they'll go like
this and they'll widen their stance and
you're like oh God cuz think about it
they're doing exactly what you told them
to do knees out you you get your knees
out when you widen your stance and so
that's a frustrating experience for the
lifter when you go knees out and then
they do it and then you're like no I
didn't mean that so it's best to avoid
that situation all together by getting
it right beforehand by demonstrating to
them so here's how I'll demonstrate it
to a client I'll say okay when you are
doing the squat I want you to descend
down with your knees tracking over the
middle of your toes so if you watch my
knees will stay in alignment with the
middle of my toes the whole way through
the the exercise and so watch all right
I come down I come down I come down I
get to the bottom usually most people
track correctly up until here and then
when the movement reverses when the
Ecentric reverses to the concentric
component this is when they tend to Cave
so they'll you'll see this like that and
that is called knee valgus or vus
collapse or knee caving so we show them
that and say that is not what you want
you do not want your knees to Cave you
do not not want to go like this so when
I when I tell you knees out what I mean
is force those knees out you're using
your hip muscles to get those knees out
okay and then you rise up so I want to
see those knees tracking over the toes
here's where they'll tend to collapse at
the very B botom so the very bottom of
the movement remember knees out right at
the
bottom and that is a good way of
demonstrating it beforehand so then they
know when you say knees out they know
what you're talking about and they don't
just go like this and widen their
stance so um the other thing I want to
talk about with queuing is um and I've
learned this through looking through my
my clients book books they're training
journals and I'll see little notes that
I that I um that they make with their
form cuz I'll give them you know tips
with their form and I tell them write it
down next to your you know next to your
sets and Reps so that next time you
perform the exercise you can look back
and you can see um you know what you
need to work on and they'll say
something they'll write something
totally different than me and I'll ask
them what did you mean by this and
they'll say it means don't do this but
they word it differently than me so I
try to learn their language and learn
how they um you know cue how they think
of their queuing because that's the most
effective queue for them you know one
person might say knees out um but to
this person might comprehend it better
if you say something totally different I
can't think of anything at the moment
but um anyway I've had success with
asking clients what is this what's how
would you describe that and then I
remember it next time I'm training them
and I I use that phrase instead so and
and this pertains to all of our typical
cues push through the heels knees out
chest up sit back squeeze the glutes all
those things that we tend to say as
coaches um you know those work for the
majority of people as long as you're
demonstrating it before the rep before
the set but um anyway take home points
always demonstrate the exercise before
the set tell them exactly what you mean
and then find the right cue for the
person because not everyone reacts the
same way to the same queue hope you
enjoyed the video